[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of samādhi, composing the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, some people say, some practitioners say that samādhi comes about, it's something that comes about because of passive, passivity, like a passive observation of thoughts and just relaxing, not doing anything about anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just watching the mind and the thoughts come and go, and just relaxing, eh... watching the breath, not focusing on the breath, trying to get something, just watching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, do you have to make an active effort to compose your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, well, the first one, it's... it sounds almost like a... like a, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Artificial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a privilege that comes on account of the safe, protected environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can afford to just observe your impulses and so on, when there isn't anything too impulsive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But would you remain equally
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able, amidst of a pressuring mind, overwhelming anxiety, fear, panic or lust, would you need to go to your special meditation place, room, environment, to calm down from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or would you there and then, in that very spot, remain unmoved internally?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the kind of the slippery slope.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yes, you need some degree of artificial environment that will prevent your senses from being bombarded by unsuitable sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, so that you can begin, you know, swimming upstream, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people don't know where that line is, and then the artificial environment just becomes basically my safe, comfortable space, where nothing will bother me internally either.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they feel justified in accepting such space, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they feel safe in developing such samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the moment circumstances change, like, there was no samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just, as I said, artificially keeping together the preferable environment that wasn't as disturbing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can ask yourself that, like, after your, you know, whatever you invested in your meditation practice, in your practice of samādhi, are you now
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you find yourself amidst crowd, noise, unpleasant people.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not in a position to sit down, count your breath, feel sensations, none of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no access to any of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you can't do anything about it internally or externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are in these unfavorable circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you now more
[SPEAKER_01]: Or less overwhelmed than before you started meditating.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have no access to your meditation technique, no access to your retreat place, no access to the monastery, no access to the nature free from other people, and those things start coming up, how bothersome is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you know, a person needs to be honest, to...
[SPEAKER_01]: To kind of really get to the bottom of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when the suttas describe samādhi, they always unequivocally, very clearly say, not being moved by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, they used to move you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your samādhi should be... should be the result of your training towards immovability in regard to things they want to move you by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you train in that regard, the more you make the right choices, don't allow the animal to stray, go too far, the more of a right samādhi you will have as a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, it's an indirect development.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, once you have enough of that indirect development, once you have enough of the samādhi nimitta, to put it that way, you can take that up directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes an available thing that you could attend to rightly and cultivate on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, like the simile of the chariot in the Sutta says, there is no samādhi until virtue is purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your choices and actions by body and speech are purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will lead to the purification of the mind, the samādhi, which will then lead to the purification of the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same works for the right view as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right view, it's not like just some out-of-the-blue insight, just comes from nowhere, and then you start practicing rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you start practicing rightly, or rather, you know that you're practicing rightly when you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to get to the right view, you need to develop the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to develop the right samādhi in the suttas, you need to develop the right virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to develop the right virtue, you need to stop acting out of sensuality, spilling out, by body, by speech, mentally, feeling absolved from responsibility for your sensual acts, feeling absolved from responsibility for your ill-will, accepting partial responsibility, saying, yeah, yeah, I know I shouldn't have, but, you know, justifying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there's no excuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the practice of the dhamma is the goal,
[SPEAKER_01]: The internal criteria must be, anytime I act out of any desire, any ill will, any distraction, that's entirely on me, and that is always an obstruction to unification of the mind, which is always an obstruction to the purification of the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why those who train in it, they don't have to wish for sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be the result of the right training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to...
[SPEAKER_00]: A person can be, say, just on a retreat, watching their breath and relaxing and not getting involved in distractions or whatever, sensual distractions, and the mind calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a kind of... there is a composure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... Definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, as soon as noise enters the picture, you get a phone call from your mother complaining about something you did or whatever, your composure is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is not the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means that what you were doing wasn't right.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no denial that creating the favorable circumstances will pacify the animal, will calm the mind down.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not samādhi we speak about.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just, as I said, a conditional pacification of otherwise equally wild and unwise animal and citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everybody starts like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is like, do you think that's the samādhi that the Buddha was teaching in the suttas?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you know that the samādhi from the actual suttas is a lot more than that?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, go on your retreats, and by all means, cultivate the right environment that will not bombard you with unsuitable things, so that you have to fend them off all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you will at least know that, okay, this is just a stepping stone towards the right samādhi and the right practice and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not going to be born out of it magically.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I just protect this special environment long enough, mind will somehow magically discover right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right samādhi comes as a result of right training and virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you use that environment and your retreat place and so on to start training those right choices, right virtue, right values that would then
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of pertain back to your life outside of the retreat, outside of the special environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would continue making the same choices of non-greed, of non-lust, non-ill-will, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your retreat is about rewriting the values of mental choices that spill down into verbal and physical actions, then yes, do as many retreats as you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your retreat is about recharging your batteries so that you can go back and enjoy the sensual life of ill-will and unrestrained mind and everything else, then that's not a retreat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly not the one that can lead to actual uprooting of suffering and understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just say this other...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's a silly view that I came across.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the idea that, you know, if you keep your environment nice and neat, uncluttered, this is conducive to inner peace, to that inner samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, externally you have this beautiful place, now everyone's nice to you, and you feel...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, samādhi is measured by...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, does that mean a wealthy person who has many servants,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a jhāna master.
[SPEAKER_01]: By that logic, he would make them so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because their house is always tidy, always neat, always clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is always on time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's so dependent on someone comes in and puts the cup the wrong way in the cupboard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of that quote-unquote practice, you ask yourself, am I more sensitive to stuff or less sensitive to stuff?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I quicker to be bothered, or bother takes a long time to arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think that's a nice measure of progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, something that would really bother me before, now it happens again, and I'm moved emotionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the nice, the best measure of progress is, imagine if a sense of control is completely taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're no more in a position to have a say in what your environment looks like.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're no more in a position to say what you will see, hear, smell, taste or touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your senses are just bombarded, I don't know, stuck in a hospital, immobile, paralyzed, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are no in a position to basically tell others what to do or what not to do or to leave you alone or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would that feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when you would be entirely just closed within yourself,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't put the blame on the external circumstances and can't change them either.
[SPEAKER_01]: How unmoved would you be internally?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the goal of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said, you begin by somewhat artificial environment that will help you keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think that artificial environment and pleasant incense and a clean room is somehow magically purifying your mind from these underlying tendencies of citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're seriously deluded, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're gonna have a rude awakening when control is taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, as you get old, sick, accidents happen, end up in the environment that is not suitable for your type of samādhi, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: samādhi that depends on external circumstances and pleasant, agreeable, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, or at least avoidance of the disagreeable ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you will see how untamed your mind actually still is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you don't want to wait for that to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't mean you need to disrupt your environment now, but you need to start internally, begin questioning it, begin contemplating scenarios.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if this environment were to change?
[SPEAKER_01]: How affected would I be by that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I still be able to maintain whatever I think my inner composure slash samādhi is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it just wouldn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: My samādhi doesn't work if there is noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: My samādhi doesn't work if there are other people doing this and if I can hear sounds or, you know, if I didn't sleep enough or if I have to work, my samādhi doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is not samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to have your samādhi work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, even if there's work, even if there's noise, even if it's a mess...
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...that I, inside, internally...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your samādhi should be unaffected by that, if it's the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no internal resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the right samādhi comes on account of right virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the right virtue that purifies the mind at least diminishes greed, aversion, distraction and acting out of those things, there will be quite a substantial samādhi established as a result of that immovability.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that cannot, does not come, as I said, out of the blue, falls from the sky.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just suddenly have this capacity to be unmoved.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become unmoved by training how not to move in regard to things that want to move you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, the suttas say that, in regard to the arahant, the one who cannot be moved by his mind, he's the one that moves his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all the other similes of, basically, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, were never the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're never the root of the disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Confusing them for being so, means maintaining your very wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, they are the root, they are causing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The major liability to suffering and all the other disturbances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, they're not the the cure to your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it won't uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They remain unchanged, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you have the privilege of, as I said, protecting and catering your environment for the rest of your life, sickness, aging, death will come and there will be the destruction of your environment, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you have the most peaceful death,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like in some dirty hospital or something, surrounded by strangers.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the shutting down of the senses that you still depend upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's gonna feel the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, better start training in it, internally, through recognition and contemplation of these scenarios, and then keeping a corner of your eye at the animal, how much it moves, how much it twitches, and conditioning it to, hold on, no, this is the actual reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's get ready for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's get ready for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How will you know if your dog is resisting something or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: By locking it inside and protecting it and never exposing it to that, to those ideas?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might remain perfectly peaceful just because you're sheltering it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you are not able to shelter it, the same old beast will come up and cause the damage and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you shelter it, so that it doesn't escape, but then you actually have to start recollecting, providing these ideas, in order for it to learn how to be peaceful within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, the disturbance does not come from the circumstances, it comes from the resistance of the citta, patīgā.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's fully trained out of the citta, then it's just peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter what condition you're in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is Adahantyu.